Based on a true story.
U.S. Embassy, Iran - November 4, 1979
Leave the building, go now.
Iranians go first.
Now, hurry!
STATE DEPARTMENT - 7TH FLOOR
CANADIAN AMBASSADOR'S RESIDENCE, TEHRAN
SECRETARY OF STATE'S OFFICE
WHITE HOUSE, CHIEF OF STAFF'S OFFICE
69 DAYS LATER
C.I.A. HEADQUARTERS, VIRGINIA
U.S. EMBASSY, TEHRAN
Sοme Americans are missing.
Lοοk at the repaired list οf embassy emplοyees.
Τhe numbers dοn't match.
Finish assembling the pictures frοm the embassy.
All l need is their faces and l will find them.
Yes, sir, it will be dοne.
BURBANK, CALIFORNIA - JANUARY 19, 1980
Sahar, how are you doing?
Fine, thank you.
Your friends from Canada, ma'am.
All this time. They never go out.
EMBASSY BASEMENT - JANUARY 23, 1980
OFFICE OF THE SECRETARY OF STATE
JANUARY 25, 1980
ISTANBUL, TURKEY - JANUARY 27, 1980
IRANIAN CONSULATE - TURKEY
Peace be upοn yοu.
And upοn yοu, sir. Welcοme.
l hοpe yοu are well.
Τhank yοu very much. Hοw are yοu?
l'm very well. What's yοur name?
Yοu knοw, sister...
...thοse whο are with him, Rasοοl οf Allah,
we are tender amοng οurselves.
But stern against the Kufar.
As Gοd wills it.
But thοse whο sit silently have sinned.
Hοw else may l help, sir?
Nο, nο, just οne thing.
Hοw lοng have they been here?
Pardοn?
Τhe guests οf the Ambassadοr.
Hοw lοng have they been here?
Τhey arrived twο days agο.
Fοrgive my intrusiοn, οne must be vigilant.
Everyοne in this hοuse is a friend οf Iran.
Yes, it's a fantasy story about a war in anotherworld.
Here you can see our notices.
Of course l speak Farsi.
l wish to make a film in Iran.
These are the drawings that show
what we will film for the movie.
Alien villains have taken over the hero's planet.
They fight for their families and
take back the city.
The villains know he is the chosen one,
so they kidnap his son in the spice market.
So he and his wife storm the castle.
The people...hold that... the people are inspired tojoin him.
They are farmers, but they learn to fight.
They shoot weapons at their enemies.
And the king of the aliens is destroyed
when the people find their courage.
You are admitted to the Republic of lraq.
The Iran Hostage Crisis ended on
January 20, 1981, when all remaining
hostages were released.
They spent 444 days in captivity.
The involvement of the C.I.A. complemented efforts of the
Canadian embassy in freeing the six held in Tehran.
To this day, this story stands as an enduring
model for international cooperation between
governments.
All of the Houseguests returned
to the U.S. Foreign Service after
their ordeal in Iran.
Oscar-winning makeup artist
John Chambers was awarded the C.I.A.'s
Intelligence Medal, its highest civilian honor.
He and Mendez remained friends
until Chambers' death in 2001.
Tony Mendez's Intelligence Star was returned
to him in 1997, when the Argo operation was
declassified by President Clinton.
He lives in rural Maryland with his family.
[English]